(audience speaks indistinctly)
- Welcome, everybody. Thank you for being here.
If you're just walking in,
hopefully, you've seen your event app,
and you know that things were adjusted
and pushed back just a little bit
to accommodate for all the engaging dialogue and information
that we got, including...
How excited are you about the Google announcement?
- Whoo (applauds)! - Woo-hoo!
- I think that's gonna be a game changer,
and it gives us a lot of access
and some good things coming for our students.
So, thank you for joining us.
This is "The Practical Use of AI for College Workflows."
Again, if you're just joining us, we're start...
The panels right now in the morning
are from 11:30 to 12:30,
and lunch will be from 12:30 to 1:30,
so you'll still have time.
And right now, the afternoon schedule remains the same
as it was in your event app.
I wanna thank you all for joining us.
I wanna thank our panelists.
This is "Practical Use of AI for College Workflows."
I'll introduce them briefly in a moment.
But all our panelists' information
is in your app, so you can read
about their wonderful accomplishments and background.
But I wanna just take a moment
to let you know who we have here on the stage
before I get started.
We have Dave Johnston.
We have Jory Hadsell, Amanda Marshall, Joel Bennett,
Ger Xiong, and Allison Maricic,
and they will tell you where they're from.
You'll see that when they show their slides
in just a moment.
But we are here today
to continue the conversation that started in the morning
of what is the potential for AI
and how can it help us
and how can it help our students.
One of the things that we have been talking about around AI
is how do we build capacity, eh?
A lot of our colleges and institutions, we have processes.
We have workflows. We have problems with our workflows.
How do we make sure we build capacity
and work with AI to help us build that capacity?
And our panelists today are going to talk
about some use cases
and showcase what they're doing
at their colleges and institutions
in order to tell us
how they're building capacity
and helping their institution
with certain processes and workflows.
What we hope to do today
is highlight and showcase some of those use cases.
And then after the panelists present you with their ideas,
I'm gonna ask 'em some questions,
and time permitting, we'll let the audience
ask some questions, as well.
All right? So let's get started.
I'm gonna hand it off first to Dave Johnston.
- Good morning.
Hopefully, it's working. There we go.
Okay, fifty-fifty on the remote.
- Well, Dave, first of all,
as we're fifty-fifty on the remote, you can go head.
I know that when we talked you said
that your IT team was getting particularly overwhelmed,
especially around the start of a semester,
especially when there were a lot of common calls,
questions that were inundating your staff.
So based on that, what did you do to find a solution?
- Thank you, if you could advance,
since this wasn't (indistinct).
So, yeah, like all of you, there's never enough IT people,
and for Mendocino....
I'm at Mendocino College,
so we're about two hours north of San Francisco
up in the Redwoods.
We have...
The two weeks before the semester starts,
the two weeks after the semester starts,
nobody remembers their password,
so we're getting a million calls for password resets.
"I can't remember how to get on the Wi-Fi,
even though it was just on there
for the summer session," or in the spring.
And so we have this explosion of tickets.
And so we have a small IT team, small but mighty,
but we really need help.
And then the other issue, I think,
particularly, you know, post-pandemic, is this expectation
of support outside of the normal eight-to-five business day.
Our students now, you know, are calling the help desk
at two o'clock in the morning
and getting the answering machine.
And so that's been a challenge for us.
We've done some work with extended hours
to, you know, try to stagger our staff
so we can go into six or seven at night,
but obviously, we can't be there
when students are gonna be there.
And just this...
The techs spend an inordinate amount
of time at the beginning of the semester
on these just tier-one kind of tickets.
So what we did is...
I'll try this (indistinct). There I go!
So, we worked with Invoke Learning,
which is a partner we were already working with
on a data lakehouse.
And so they had a solution
that is basically a tech support bot.
The bot can handle phone calls and emails.
It can also do wonderful video conferences,
but I didn't wanna pay for the video,
so we do phone and email,
which is how our students are used to contacting us.
So the bot is integrated with our systems.
It can do password resets for students, and if...
It has a knowledge base of, you know, just all
the typical tier-one kinds of tickets that we get.
Additionally, if they can't help a student,
it can open a ticket in our ticket system,
and if it's during business hours,
it can transfer them to the human help desk.
So it's been a really nice addition for us.
And I think my...
The folks that normally handle those tier-one phone calls...
It's been a little quiet, a little bit eerie, for them,
I think, this semester.
The other thing, for us,
that's really been beneficial is we...
We're a Hispanic-serving institution.
About 38% of our students are Hispanic,
and we have one programmer analyst in my department
that speaks Spanish.
And so he was spending...
You know, we were coming to transfer people to him.
He doesn't really know how to answer those IT questions,
but at least, he speaks Spanish.
It was a challenge.
And so the nice thing about the bot
is that it does speak Spanish.
We actually had to iterate a while
to find a Spanish voice that we really liked.
I think one of the better ones that wasn't quite there
was the Swedish person speaking Spanish.
But anyway, we did finally get one we liked,
and we're in the process now.
We've worked with our ESL faculty
on identifying some additional languages.
So we'll be a...
The current model's there's 17 languages.
And so we're gonna bring in another six languages,
but for us, the Spanish was a huge piece.
And so I know...
There's probably questions about the nerdy bits.
So the way it works
is Invoke Learning basically spins up an instance
of the bot.
The bot connects to the existing data
we already had in the Invoke system,
so they created views specifically for the bot
to get the pieces of information needed,
like student ID, date of birth, phone numbers, emails,
those sorts of things.
It connects to Entra,
so it can go ahead and do the password reset.
Then we provided a knowledge base of information,
you know, PDFs, Word docs
of those typical kinds of questions and answers,
explaining the process for getting on the Wi-Fi,
explaining how to get into Canvas,
how to get through our SSO- - Sure. Thank you.
- self-service enrollment.
So all those kinds of things are in the knowledge base,
so it can-
- Thank you. - answer those questions
as well.
And as I mentioned, it connects to the ticket system,
uses the API to get there,
and if it needs to,
it'll transfer a call during business hours.
And so it's been a really nice system for us.
We've only been using it about a month,
so I'm hoping as we get into spring
we'll really see more of a benefit.
We do get students that wanna talk to a human,
and that that's okay,
but there's a large number of them
that do stick with the bot,
and there's actually been some...
We get to see all of the calls.
I can see the text. I can also listen recordings.
But there's been a few longer calls
where the student starts out frustrated
but by the end they're thanking the bot
for helping them with their problem.
And so it's nice to see those positive reactions, so yep.
- All right, thank you.
I think all of our institutions
have small but mighty IT teams
and could learn from this use how to build some capacity.
Jory, I know
that the California Community Colleges have been
in the news recently
around fraudulent students,
and I know that Foothill-De Anza had to tackle this problem.
So can you talk a little bit
about the problem that our district,
Foothill-De Anza Community College District, faced
and how you started to solve that and used AI?
- Sure, yeah. Good to see everyone here.
And obviously, I love workshops
that are focused on really practical solutions,
right, that solve problems,
so I'll kick off a little bit of a story,
and you might hear some different arcs to the story
as we kinda go down the line here.
But like many of our institutions,
at Foothill-De Anza, in January of 2024,
we were hit particularly hard with fraud.
It wasn't necessarily surprise, because we'd been hearing
from other institutions around the state.
There's, you know, the quiet whispers between CTOs
or between other leadership folks
where we knew that this was a problem.
And so timing-wise, you know,
we were seeing this surge of fraudulent applications
coming in to our institutions,
and we had just started on a different project,
in fact, working on a beta project
along with our friends here from West Valley-Mission
and Ivy Tech Community College as well.
But when this problem popped up...
I will never forget being in the meeting
with our admissions and financial aids officers
from our two colleges,
just saying, like, "Jory, we have to think differently
about how to solve this solution.
We're pulling our hair out.
We're exhausting our staff."
Oh thank you for...
I think I mighta messed it up.
Lemme go back to the problem.
See, don't let a technologist have a remote, 'cause...
Interesting things happening.
And so we talked with our partners at N2N.
We'd worked with N2N before
on the California Virtual Campus,
so nearly all of our colleges in the state
have an integration through N2N.
We said, "Gosh, can we leverage that
so that we could have a quick...
You know, get something in place.
Test it out quickly
without having to do a lotta deep infrastructural work."
And so we looked at, you know, the challenges,
whether it was students can't get their courses,
staff burning out, financial risk,
and reputational risk, right, for our colleges.
And so what we did
was we partnered with N2N.
We brought in our subject matter experts
from Student Services and from our IT staff.
Shout out to a couple of our staff who are in the room here.
I see Jarrick, and I see a few other folks
who worked heavily on this project.
And we said, "Okay, if we're gonna use AI,
what's the number-one thing we can do to train the model?
Let's use some historical data."
So we fed it a couple of years' worth of historical data
to be able to understand what some
of the patterns looked like.
We validated that with our staff
because they were on the front lines
and seeing on a daily basis
what the changing tactics were that were coming in.
And so as a result,
we got to a place
where we felt confident
that we could run this behind the scenes
for our fall registration last year.
We ran it side by side
with our in-house-developed legacy fraud model
and we actually discovered double the amount
of what we thought we had.
So that's the power of AI, being able
to look across these data sets and find these patterns.
So, through the collaboration, my friend Joel here said,
"You know what? We'll take that.
Right? And we'll test it."
And so we began this multi-district collaboration.
And then we had Santiago Canyon come on board,
and some other districts as well,
because there was this sort of quiet network
of all of us trying to share solutions.
So I think the story is, you know,
working with existing partners
if they have capabilities you can quickly leverage,
being able to move quickly
in a way that's thoughtful and careful
but with other partnerships.
We've benefited so much from knowing
that your district was seeing the same types
of results that we were seeing
and that others that came on afterward...
Like, it just continues to validate and improve the model.
And so today, we have, I believe,
83 colleges now in our system
that are using this solution,
the LightLeap solution.
It's just...
Like, sometimes, you find something that works,
and you go with it.
And so we've been really excited about that.
And so again, the cross-district piece is
critically important, and I just wanted to share that
as part of our journey.
- Thank you.
Amanda and Joel, I know
that West Valley-Mission Community College District
had this project that they were also working on,
but I know that you also saw some other needs
where you could use AI as a solution,
so lemme ask you: what made you wanna explore
using AI with your Student Services areas
and to support them?
- Yeah, great question. Thank you.
Hi, everyone. So, I'm Amanda Marshall.
I am the assistant director of our EOPS and CARE programs
at Mission College, right down the street.
And a couple years ago, when I came into my position,
I was kind of taking a landscape of the student journey
in terms of gaining access to our programs and services.
And so we have about 10 what we call success communities
so EOPS; TRIO; MESA;
our APIDA Affinity Groups, Umoja, Puente.
And then we also have our Basic Needs services,
our Career Center mental health services.
And so students were submitting different applications
for each program and service
or interest forms and then applications, right?
And then we were taking a very siloed approach
to determining eligibility
and communicating with students
and accepting them into programs.
So, this was, you know, creating duplication of services,
where we're serving lotta the same students.
We're not broadening our reach.
We don't really know who's eligible for our programs.
We're asking the students to jump through a lotta hoops
just to get, like, to the point of connection, right?
And so I actually created a centralized form
for all of our programs and services,
so we call it the Mission Support Form,
and we use kinda the lowest common denominator
of what everybody needs in terms of eligibility criteria.
And part of the difficulty, then,
in having students fill out that form
is, like, okay, there's also backend data that we need
and some of it is in CCApply
and some of it is in this other system
and some of it's over here.
And so we are tracking down
and accessing different systems
to try to find eligibility information.
And then we're still all working in silos, right?
So we've tried to combine it into this giant spreadsheet
where then people are deleting things and moving things
and things are getting lost
and people are super overwhelmed.
It's hard to keep track.
We had duplicate submissions.
We had, you know, people putting the wrong information,
the incorrect ID number, their...
You know, so we spent so much time
just trying to clean up data
and find accurate data to figure out
whether or not students were eligible for programs.
And then it took us so much longer to get back to them.
And when we did communicate, it was a lot of back and forth
of, like, "we still need pieces from you"
or "we need you to clarify this."
So it was taking very long to get students connected,
and we were literally looking at this
like "there has to be a better way," right?
So the solution was to integrate AI.
- Great, I'm Joel Bennett, director,
Educational Technology at West Valley-Mission.
So, typical problem, right?
We have college administrators and staff
struggling with our platforms,
like Banner and others, right,
so developing shadow IT processes
because the existing platforms don't work.
So what we wanted to do
was create a single pane of glass for these staff, right,
just the cognitive load
of having to go to Argos and Banner
and gather all this information.
Before they even talk to a student, they're exhausted
from just having to gather the data,
so the first piece was working with N2N
to develop a dashboard with all the data they need.
Then the second part was...
Okay, all these programs have key eligibility
to see if they're qualified or not.
And so we trained AI
to assess student data
and determine whether they're eligible,
so for TRIO,
they have to be a first-gen college student, right?
They have to be a STEM major.
We train the model on each one of these programs,
so now it can go through the student data
and determine and make an assessment:
"Is the student qualified or not qualified?"
And then let the advisors know,
and they can do the human assessment, right, verify.
And we flag those parts of any student's data that shows
that they're not qualified, they're not met, right?
So, great success there.
It goes through all kinds of student data,
GPA, majors, financial aid status,
'cause each one of these programs
has unique eligibility status, or requirements.
So again, advisors see
clear AI-generated breakdown of eligibility.
What's the impact? Right?
Now, Amanda and others can focus
on student outreach and communication
and providing the service,
not fiddling around and being overwhelmed by data.
And so just based on Amanda's assessment,
you know, this is saving her five hours a week.
There's 13 different advisors working on Mission Cares,
so once all 13 advisors are using it,
we're looking at saving 3,000 staff hours a year,
so there you go.
Oh, sorry.
I did the Jory.
Okay, so, yeah, this one, really, we kinda phrase this
as, you know, "what's the problem? What's the solution?"
But I also have "what's next?" right? Deeper integration.
So, we're working with specific programs
that we kind of didn't hit as well on the first phase,
so we're looking to pull in more data from Banner
to help some of the other programs.
We're working on making AI chat, right?
You can only fit so much data into a dashboard.
We want these advisors to be able to say,
"Tell me about Keith Smith.
Show me all the students that I have reached out to
that haven't responded,"
so that's what we're aiming next, yeah,
and then doing more early alert stuff,
reaching out proactively to students,
like, "You've registered?
Hey, you may be available to you.
Yes, based on the data we have on you,"
so there ya go.
- All right, thank you.
I think you guys can all sense a theme here.
Is this resonating with what's going on
at your institutions?
There's data validation, redundancies, duplication.
We're all facing these challenges.
And so I'll turn it over to you, Ger, right now.
What's happening at Palo Alto?
And what problem did your institution face?
And how are you going to use AI to solve that?
- Only during.
- Oh, whoops.
- Sorry. - (indistinct) clawing
to that. - Sorry.
- Claw it back.
- Who's a tech person?
- Thank you. Hi, good morning.
My name is Ger Xiong. I'm the dean of Student Services.
I oversee financial aid, admissions records, and counseling.
A bit of background about us.
Can you go back a little bit?
We are, like, the rural college.
We are located in Blythe, California,
right between border of California and Arizona.
We're just on the California side,
and we have about 2,500 FTES,
and that equates to about 26,000 enrollments.
Half of our student population
are incarcerated Rising Scholars.
We serve six CDCR locations in the state of California,
three in SoCal
and then, of course, three in Northern California.
And of course, about 35 to 40% of our students
are are also Fire Science students,
meaning, especially for our Rising Scholars students,
they don't have internet access, right?
We are paper-based.
Everything is manual. We mail them our paper applications.
They mail it back to us.
If there's errors or you can't read it,
we mail it back to them to correct it.
By the time it gets back to us,
classes are no longer available for them to register.
It's a heavy manual process.
And so when I came in
along with my vice president, Clint Cowden,
we had a half-day session with A and R,
and we found out that the biggest struggle and challenge
that we had with admissions records
is this manual process
of entering everything paper-based into Colleague
line by line.
That just took up a whole lot of time.
On average, we have about 500 applications annually.
For peak seasons, we have about 800.
And key issues that we have:
bad handwriting, right?
If a student puts down, "I'm in Yard A,"
we can see that and say, "Maybe that says Yard F,"
or sometimes, instead of putting the yard location,
they put, "Prison" or "CDCR," whatever it is, right?
There's also human errors in entering in this data.
It's extremely time-consuming
and also essentially just not an efficient workflow, right?
There's also implications of data integrity,
and that really impacts our IR office as well.
So, one of the things that we did...
And luckily, we actually met N2N at a different conference
sometime last year or about last year,
and in talking about these sorts of challenges, we thought,
"Let's look at N2N," essentially.
What N2N has done for us
is better streamline our process, right?
So when we get these stacks of applications
that come in on a weekly basis,
we scan it up to our N2N platform.
From there, they then extract these handwritten data
into our SIS system directly.
When they're able to do that,
when the staff opens it up,
we can compare the scanned documents
with what's populated,
and there's actually an accuracy meter.
So say, for example, the name is like 90% accurate.
Generally, 90% accurate, in my mind, is pretty accurate.
If it's like 85 or 80 or below,
we double-check those, right?
And staff essentially goes and just compares it, checks it,
and finally, like, approve the information.
We went live about like three to four weeks ago,
and thus far, it's been the most exciting thing
for our staff
because, again, it really has cut down the manual process
of these applications that come in.
And so we're doing it for our Rising Scholars population
and also for our Fire Science population.
And I must say, for our Fire Science population,
you would think, "Well, they are firefighters.
You know, they have open access to internet.
They can do this in CCApply";
however, the preference is paper, right?
And we have to be good stewards,
and we have to provide excellent customer service
'cause we're talking about at least 1,000 FTES.
If we lose Fire Science, that's impacting jobs, right?
And so they have been very vocal about "you know what?
Our firefighters are good with paper applications.
They're better with that."
And so we have continued to use paper applications for them.
But again, I think our...
And finding N2N as a solution to process this
has been night and day for us.
And so we're just really thrilled
to really showcase that here.
- Thank you, Ger.
I think this is a great example again
of how are we utilizing AI
to still meet students where they are,
because if they don't have the resources they're gone
and we still want to impact them.
And so meeting them where they are
but still finding solutions for our employees
is really important.
And Allison, I believe
you, also at Santiago Canyon, had some issues
with manual entry and delays.
And so I'll hand it to you.
I'll be the remote right now.
- I just wanna say to my fellow panelists and the audience,
this is my clicker that I offered to share,
and obviously, that was a bad idea, so sorry.
Thought I was being helpful, but it's okay.
We can just keep with our normal process.
Hello, everyone, my name is Allison Maricic.
I'm the counselor/coordinator
of Apprenticeship at Santiago Canyon College.
So, when I came into my role...
My position is very new,
so I came into my position last year,
and one of the things that I noticed
as I was kind of taking the lay of the land,
as we talked about earlier,
is where were some of the gaps
in terms of how people are evaluated in terms of our numbers
and how we're serving our students.
So one of the biggest gaps that I found
was that our apprenticeship students,
which encompasses a big part
of our population as a campus...
We're a big apprenticeship program
at Santiago Canyon College,
for those of you that don't know,
and our students' numbers
when we look at our graduation rates
weren't reflecting what our students were actually doing
at their training centers and journeying out, right?
So I was like, "Well, why isn't this happening?
Why don't we see these reflections of that?"
And one of the things that we found
was that the manual process, right,
of going into evaluating
the graduation and the completion of the students
was very time-consuming.
Because of the nature of traditional trades,
the training is typically done offsite, right?
It's not done at our college.
It's done through the training centers
of the different locations:
carpentry, electrician, for example.
And one of the things that happens
is that that information is sent
through a very old-school process
of how the training trust like
to send their information over to us.
And then we have to manually input that information.
And then from there, at the end,
students end up with two transcripts,
one from the training trust and then one from our college,
where our transcript at the end wasn't always reflective
of what they actually did in their training,
so we had to find a solution.
And so one of the things that we found
was that my counselor and my colleagues were
spending hours to, sometimes, weeks
processing one student,
so when we have thousands...
Right now, we have a population
of a little over 5,000 current apprentices at our campus.
Those students are graduating all of the time,
and our numbers were not reflecting that.
So luckily, we were able to connect and collaborate with N2N
and talk about this particular issue
and what we can do to help kind of bring forward
their platform and their model
to help us kind of break through these barriers,
these, like, manual processing bottlenecks,
very similar things to what my colleagues have shared,
so that our students can get the certificates
that they deserve, right?
They are eligible for a certificate of achievement,
and they also have the ability
to get an associate's degree
in their apprenticeship programs
if they have general education,
and the students were just not getting the right access,
even though they had completed the programs.
So we were able to first kind of see...
Well, what can we do?
How can we kind of break down this process?
Well, in our collaboration, our proposed solution...
I'll say that, out of, I think, everyone here,
we have not yet gone live.
So, we are still kind of in the planning stages,
but we're very close to being able to kind of test this out.
But we're really excited about what we see so far
in terms of what we will be able to do
with this integration,
and I think this has a lot of amazing implications
for many of your colleges
if we think about just transcript evaluation
as a whole, right?
All of us get other college transcripts,
whether you have apprenticeship programs or not,
that you have to figure out how they fit into your programs,
so this has amazing implications for everyone.
But for us, what the...
One of the great things
that the model and the platform is able to bring to us
is that it brings everything to one place.
So one of the things that is difficult
is that we, again, have these outside transcripts.
We have, you know, missing information.
And so it's able to
bring it all forward into one place
so we can see all of the information together.
One of the other great things that this has helped us do
is kind of look at our internal processes
is how can we better support our students
and how can we break down some of the barriers
of how we're processing paperwork just for graduation.
So I would say, on a side note,
that's been an amazing thing, to be able to connect
with all of the different departments on our campus
that connect students to completing their program,
and we've been able to collaborate
and take out multiple forms,
where now it's just one single form.
And so now we're able to use that one single form
that now combines multiple forms that we had do in the past
within this integration
so that all of the information is on one page.
And that took our campus to really be on board
with how can we better support our internal process
so that this could work.
It goes both ways. And so yes, the technology helps.
But we also have to be open
to how do we envision this change
and what do we need to do as a campus
to kind of think about what we can do
just within our daily work.
And so with that, the other piece
that we were able to really think about, too,
is integrating CPL, credit for prior learning.
So, one of the things
that we built into this process, as well, is...
For our apprenticeship students,
one of the things that happens
is that the training trust does CPL,
and they've been doing CPL for a long time,
way longer than we even been thinking about it.
When a student goes into a carpentry training trust
to be indentured,
they are evaluated on their previous work experience,
and they can skip levels, right, and then indenture out.
We didn't have a process in place for those gaps,
when the students didn't have that coursework
when they indentured higher.
So now within this system
and now within this integration with N2N,
we're able to build, within that, again, singlized form, CPL
into this process, so it's really exciting we're able
to kind of, again, bring in a lot of internal processes
plus build this through, so we're excited.
The other piece that's really cool about this,
that was probably the best thing
that Kiran showed us, at N2N, recently...
His team was able to show us that our internal form
that we created to graduate students that minimized...
The system is actually able to automate all
of the fields and information within that PDF
so that everything is be able to be verified and checked
but can be sent over
directly to our admissions and records team
once our counselors have reviewed it
so taking down a lot of not only processing steps
but people that have to kind of stop
and check each of these different levels.
So we're really excited.
Stay tuned as we, you know, have the opportunity
to kind of see what the outcomes will be
and what we're able to build this from moving forward,
but I think a lotta of great implications
for everyone in the room.
- Thank you. Thank you all for sharing.
I hope this is starting to give you ideas of where some
of your pain points and processes
might benefit from some AI solutions,
but I wanna throw this question out
because some of you touched on it a little bit.
We all know at our institutions that change is hard.
It's hard to get people to do things differently.
Are you from an institution where it's easy?
Oh, I was hoping we'd have some examples.
Change is hard, so I'm gonna ask...
I'm just gonna throw it out to the panelists.
Knowing that change is hard
and even though you're doing something
or trying to deploy a solution
or develop a solution
that will help build capacity and improve workloads,
what challenges or roadblocks did you face?
And how did you overcome that to help move people along?
- Yeah, so I think one of the key challenges
is this technology is new
and some key stakeholders within our organization
have been used to building, or buying, stuff
that's basically shelfware, right?
But this solution was custom built with a trusted partner,
but it took some time to develop,
and that was a key thing to overcome.
We had a few false starts.
But then we got some buy-in
from the president of Mission College,
and that helped kind of push it forward for us, so.
- Well, I'll go next.
Yeah, I think that one of the components
in this project and in others
is we have a lotta really dedicated professional staff
at our colleges, who...
You know, some of...
I kinda think about it like the middle layer
of our institutions,
where a lotta these processes are handled.
They've evolved over time,
and our professional staff have a lotta pride
in the work that they're doing
and their ability to support some of these processes
that, frankly, they probably don't even like,
but they're able to hold up the layers of the cake.
And so I think one of the components of that
was being able to present them
with a solution, or a proposed solution,
that would, like, functionally ease their workload, right,
being able to give them something very practical
that had a real impact on how they do their job
and to let them focus
on other areas of their job they'd rather do,
whether it's interacting with students
or whether it's providing other services.
So I think that's a really...
That was a real key takeaway for me
was, you know, we can go to AI conferences,
we can talk about academic integrity issues, we could talk
about the big front-of-the-line kinda items.
But from a really practical standpoint,
I think just finding tweaks and things
that can help people do their job more effectively
and allow them...
I'm super impressed by your solution, right,
to be able to say,
"Hey, this is also helping our students,
like, get their credential faster," right?
So everyone (indistinct).
- Yeah, I was just gonna say, the other piece
when we talk about roadblocks,
and I think I've noticed this
with some of my colleagues as well,
is that, sometimes, it's within our institution
but then also outside of our, like, institution, right?
Like, we're taking in, for example...
For apprenticeship, right, there's a lot
of different programs and people,
and they have their own processes
and how they run things
and ways that they wanna potentially modernize or not.
So how can we adjust to that
while still serving our students?
I think all of us have kinda shown
how we can kind of find "okay, well,
this has been a problem for a long time.
This is something that we can do about it,"
where before these tools came about
we really didn't have a lot of options.
We just kinda had to make use with what we had.
- I think one of the challenges that we're facing is...
I'm gonna blame it on the old web chat bot we had.
It wasn't very good.
So, I think it got a reputation of not being helpful.
We've actually replaced that now,
so we have a different web chat now, which is now helpful.
But I think people calling into the AI tech support bot...
I think they're jumping to human faster,
and I think it's probably because of experiences
with the web chat bot,
not realizing it's different technology.
So I think part of our challenge
is gonna be to overcome that immediate go-to-human
and to have it get a reputation across campus
that it's helpful and useful,
and I think, over time, we'll accomplish that.
- As everybody's here at this conference,
you're going to be exposed
to a lot of different solutions and products.
If you checked out the Futures Hub downstairs,
you'll see we have a lot of vendors.
And so there are a lotta options out there
for how to solve the pain points
that institutions are feeling and having.
Sometimes, it becomes then a patchwork
of having different solutions,
so I wanna either throw this out
to all of you or maybe the CTOs,
I don't know, whoever wants to answer.
But how does your particular project right now...
How does it or how will it fit into a broader AI strategy?
And has your institution addressed that?
Or is it addressing that?
- Mainly, our faculty's ignoring AI
and hoping it will go away.
- It's a strategy still.
May not be a great one, but
still a- - So still working on that.
But I think, you know, we have done a lotta work on
getting students to help when they need the help
in the way that they need help.
And so I think, for us,
this bot was kind of the natural progression
of the efforts we've made in expanding hours
and doing, you know, drop-in support
and some the other things that we've done,
so it's been kind of that natural progression.
And actually, since we've done this,
our VP of Student Services has actually come to me and said,
"What would it take to do this same thing
in admissions and records and financial aid?"
And so we're starting to have those conversations
to see how we can expand the scope of the bot
to more departments.
- Anyone else tackle that?
- I'll bite.
- Okay, thank you.
- No, I'm watching what Dave's doing at Mendocino,
and I'm like, "Why didn't we think of that?" right?
So there is a lotta this sharing that happens,
and I'm super privileged to be able
to learn from smart people like him.
I think that, from my perspective,
even if you don't know exactly where you're gonna start,
your institution can start
putting some of the fundamental pieces in place, right?
We started about a year ago, maybe a year and a half ago,
just knowing that we had too many data silos,
and we were gonna wanna use AI.
But you know, where's that gonna happen?
Where are we gonna have sorta the coalition
of the willing that wanna jump in?
And so being able to make sure
when you do take a leap with a product
that you have access to the data easily, right?
So we started consolidating our data into an infrastructure
where, you know, we could easily API into that.
We could be able to have that interoperability
between products, so I think that's...
That's really important
because there are
multiple players, right, in your institution
that are gonna have different visions
of what they wanna have happen.
But I love the example of "hey, you know"...
I don't wanna call out, you know, anyone in my own district,
but we have phone trees still, right, in certain areas,
and it's like, "Oh, I'd love
to get rid of those phone tree."
No one thinks that's a great experience for students,
so I'm gonna totally steal your idea, Dave.
- All right, I'll throw another question.
So Allison, Ger, Amanda,
you've talked about how you're directly serving students,
meeting them where they are.
At this point with your solution,
what lessons have you learned?
And what are next steps for you?
Because some of you have, like, really changed the way
that you're operating.
What are some lessons and next steps?
- Yeah, I think that one of our next steps
is to really do some analytical data
on how much this has, like, improved our process,
because we've seen some very tangible results,
even in the first, you know, semester of rolling it out.
Just shortening up the time
that students are hearing back from us,
they're able to get connected so much faster to services.
We've also been able to reduce by about 10%
the amount of students who are enrolling in the college
and then never registering for classes
or applying for financial aid,
because we're identifying them early
when they apply to the form
and we're reaching out to them.
We have a dedicated liaison in financial aid
that I work with,
where, you know, we're talking every day,
looking at the student's eligibility
because they've reached out, right?
And so we're closing all of those loops at the same time
and really working in a connected way
to make sure that those students get connected
to those services, so we're really...
We're seeing improvements there,
and we're also, you know, intentionally making connections
to our new student equity plan at the college, as well,
and seeing how it's helping to advance
specific disproportionate-impact-gap-closing
that we're looking to do, as well.
So I think those are some next steps that we're looking at
because it's just improved our process
so much across the board.
So, I think something that has been super helpful
for me in general, like, in saving time
is the communication templates
that we have automatically populated.
I spend so much time on email
going back and forth with students,
and in our system, we actually just have a notify button,
where I just pick a prepopulated template
and I send it out to the student.
And then there's a reply-to field
that automatically comes back to my email
if they wanna reach out.
And it's just honestly revolutionized the way
that we connect with students,
and it's something so simple,
but I can't wait to roll that out to other departments
so that it's freeing up time for them
to actually help resolve the student's issue
instead of drafting continuous emails to various students
and not really having a place where they can track
who they've reached out to for what.
So this has been, like, absolute game changer for us.
- I think, for us, we are doing baby steps, for sure.
Like I said, we went live about a few weeks ago,
and we've been meeting with the N2N team
almost on a weekly basis or biweekly basis
to kinda give feedback, right, on how do we...
Say, for example, if we scan a zip code.
That should automatically populate the city as well,
things like that, so essentially,
it just refining the process.
We understand that it won't be perfect yet, right?
And so I think, sometimes, on our campus,
there's this fear of, like, how do we jump
onto a software or a product
if it's not perfect yet, right?
But I think that it kind of hinders a lot
of the progress that we've been through.
And so I think, for us, it's really
trying to change that culture and change that mindset
of saying, "Hey, you know what?
Let's go ahead and adopt this."
And it's a pilot semester for us. And so that's exciting.
On a more different note,
next steps also for my VP and higher up.
It's also a question for
our CSEA union as well.
We are a union-heavy campus, right?
And although I don't sit in these meetings,
I do not doubt that these conversations are coming up
about fears of, like, "is this going
to replace our jobs essentially?" right?
And so again, fortunately, I'm not in those meetings,
but you know, I think, for me, at least on daily basis,
when I meet with my staff members who are in these unions,
it's benefiting them, or it's benefiting the way in which
they do their work, and it's a lot more efficient for them.
So we are certainly taking baby steps
and approaching it very carefully, as well, so.
- Yeah, so, I think, similarly, we have not yet gone live,
so I think, for us, we're excited
to, like, initiate that process and kind of see.
I have a specific test group that we're working with.
So, I spoke earlier
about, like, changing our internal processes
and building a lot of things,
like CPL and other things, into it.
So, myself and a colleague this summer,
we had 600-plus students that we needed to evaluate
for just one of our programs, which was carpentry.
This one tends to be the most complicated
because they have the most courses to evaluate,
and over the course of the two months in the summer,
we were only able to get through half
when we were doing it manually,
so we did over 300.
So we have the next 300 that we still need to evaluate.
And so we wanna...
So we're connecting, and that's gonna be our first group
that we're gonna go live with so that we can see,
you know, in terms of testing it directly,
same group of students,
us doing it manually as the counselors,
and then utilizing N2N,
how can we kind of see the benefit
of time and integration in all these different areas?
So we're really excited for that.
And then I think just...
I think, similarly, overcoming the fear
of it not being 100% accurate...
When we're talking about transcript evaluation,
there's so much detail that it needs to be accurate, right,
like so many of these other areas.
And so how do we overcome the fact
that we know it's never gonna be 100%
but building into our process of verification and accuracy
everything that we've been talking about with AI
and just understanding the benefits
of all of these other areas,
building that into it, and just overall building that
with the campus culture?
- Thank you.
We do have time before I throw you
the last question that I have for you.
If anybody in the audience has a question,
we have time for a question or two.
Does anyone wanna ask anything?
Yes, go ahead.
- [Audience Member] Hi.
When you were talking about fear there,
there was a really interesting,
you know, webinar, basically, that said,
"AI probably won't take your position,
but someone who knows AI probably will."
That always resonates with me.
I thought that was interesting.
But my question is more about counseling,
and I was wondering, has anyone integrated DegreeWorks
and analyzing patterns
on how students take courses to finish...
Recently, I had quite a few English students coming in
for a full literature class
that said, "Hey, I need this
for my graduation this semester."
And I said, "Okay, you know, let's look
at what you've taken and everything."
And I realized that half of 'em
really didn't need that to graduate.
They thought they did,
but they didn't understand their degree pattern
and that there were six courses that they could take,
and they just needed two for the elective.
But one of 'em resonated with me because they had waited
until the very last semester before they graduated
and just didn't realize the historical pattern
of how often these are rotated.
They're not offered every semester,
and there's a two-year plan,
but if you miss, you know, a key semester,
then you're not gonna graduate for two years.
So I'm wondering, is there some sort of effort
to create some sort of a agent or bot
where the student could analyze what classes they're taking
and maybe even ping a counselor if someone is offtrack.
- Before you answer that, lemme just summarize the question
for those in the back.
- [Audience Member] I was rambling. Sorry.
- No, it's fine.
I hope I summarize it accurately.
The question is around solutions that might integrate
either DegreeWorks or degree requirements
so that students who might miss requirements
and have to then catch up quickly,
if there's a solution to address that.
Is that close enough? Okay.
- I could take that, if you will.
Everyone, my name's Kiran Kodithala, founder and CEO.
- Here.
- Hello, everyone, my name is Kiran Kodithala,
founder and CEO of N2N, LightLeapAI platform.
So, couple of things to answer your question.
Yes, as part of the apprenticeship tracking,
it does have what's
in unofficial degree audit.
It does not use DegreeWorks,
and I'll kind of back into that in a minute.
But we can use DegreeWorks APIs if that's what you want.
The other part...
Where's Gary?
- Back. - Oh, there's Gary.
So, we're working on other very exciting stuff
with Kern Community College District
on Guided Pathways integration
that would solve exactly what you talking about,
where we have built a...
How many of you use "Waze" for maps? Right?
So the idea about "Waze" that when compared to "Google Maps"
is "Google Maps" had to go
and build a very complex billions-of-dollars architecture
to pull all the data and build out the maps
but with "Waze" you are just calling other people
that are trying to go for destination A to B.
So Guided Pathways is almost exactly like that,
where it looks
at what other students are doing, very similar to you,
but also what they were doing in that trajectory,
with respect time dimension.
So this why we are trying to shy away
from DegreeWorks or other traditional degree audit systems.
We're trying to build a historical database-modeling system.
Definitely look me up at our booth, or talk to Gary
because he's kind of my coconspirator
slash (indistinct) here.
He can explain this better than me.
But yeah, let's definitely talk, yeah.
- That booth is in the Futures Hub at N10 downstairs, so.
All right, any other questions?
Yes, go ahead.
- [Audience Member] I just had a question regarding funding,
because I know that's a topic of conversation.
What type of planning processes are you embedding
to ensure that some of these practices are sustainable?
Because I know that that's...
Some of the challenges that we're facing is...
You know, we get really excited
with all this information and technology,
but if you look into the futures,
and that might be one year, three years, or five years,
have you started thinking about that?
Or what are your planning processes with that?
- So the question is around funding and planning processes
to build in sustainability with these solutions.
- I think we're the practical- - Stunned silence?
- We're the practical users, right?
And so we're the ones that helped kinda build it.
I think those tend to be higher-up decisions.
I know it was for me.
My president was very excited,
and well, I was like, "Yes, thank you,"
so I think that's probably you.
- So, just to kick us off,
we used COVID funding to do the pilot,
And so you know, right now,
we get fraud for $3,000 per campus.
Most of the cost's covered by the state chancellor's office,
so that's great.
But it's just a proven solution, right?
We're gonna potentially save 3,000 hours.
And then it just becomes a priority for the president
of, you know, "this is a valued service you provide,
and we're doing it faster, better,
and less work for your staff,"
so it's kinda the priority, yeah.
- Yeah, I would totally echo that,
and I think, you know, as a CTO, I try to...
You know, you plan for things that aren't planned, right?
So do you have some kind of innovation fund
or some COVID money
or some pocket you can pull, you know, some resources out of
to run these proofs of concept.
Often, you can, you know, kinda negotiate that, too,
if it's something new that you're doing.
And then in terms of sustainability, though,
you bring up a really good point,
which is the life cycle
for so many technology solutions
is now so much shorter than it used to be,
so it's not "hey, we're gonna adopt something,
you know, a new degree audit system,
and we're gonna use it for five to seven or 10 years."
That whole life cycle's just so much shorter
because of the evolution of AI and technology,
so that's part of the digital transformation effort
is, you know, helping the team,
both your IT team but also your functional users,
to recognize we have to approach this differently.
We have to be a little bit more open
to solutions that, you know, maybe we haven't used before
or kind of not hold on,
like we have to so many of the technology solutions
in the (indistinct).
- All right, so the last question is
for all of you or whoever wants to answer.
Are you volunteering Dave first?
- I am. - Okay, so I guess for Dave
to start, okay.
We have a lot of institutional leaders here in the room.
Everybody probably has a pain point.
Everybody has a lens with which they view their institution
and can see that, yes, we need these solutions.
Somebody raised funding could be an issue:
"How do you even do all of these things and move change?"
So I'll ask you this: what advice do you have
for all of these institutional leaders
who are facing similar problems
or can see some of these themes
coming up at their institution?
What advice do you have
so that they can try to build some capacity
in their institution?
- Yeah, I think, you know, starting with a pilot project,
starting with a proof of concept,
starting with something small that you can do,
'cause we all have a million pain points
but maybe there's one that you can find
that you can focus on if it's a relatively low lift
but you can show some success.
But that success, I think, helps not only your internal team
feel good about what you're doing,
but also, it helps then to open the eyes
of the functional users: "Oh, gee, they did that?
And that was kind of easy, and it works very well now.
I have this other thing.
Can you help me with that?" I think.
And as IT working collaboratively with the functional teams
to try to kinda help find those solutions-
- Why you hiding all the time? - for those things
and, like said, starting small
and kind of working out from the center.
- Just going down the line.
Okay? - Go down the line, yes.
- All right, we'll do it that way. No, I agree with that.
I think finding, again, some really practical...
Doesn't have to be a huge lift
but a way you can make some of your employees' life
just a little easier.
And then it's amazing how folks will start
to come outta the woodwork,
go, "Hey, you know, I have this idea.
Could we do this with AI?"
And I find that those...
Like, pay attention to those conversations, right?
Because that's where the real nuggets come from
as folks start thinking about that
and coming forward with those ideas.
- Yeah, I would add to that.
You know, it's a very intentional change management process
when you're working with staff.
And so I think the thing that was most effective for me
was meeting with each stakeholder individually
and giving them that time and attention,
being really curious about their existing process,
and showing respect for that process, right,
'cause you're asking them to let go of it.
So I think, you know, showing respect for that process
and really using that individual one-on-one space
to get their buy-in
and really sell them on the vision for what's coming,
because I think it can be hard
to go into a meeting with a bunch of people
and share this vision and some people are like,
"I don't get it. I don't see it.
I don't understand. But what if...
I'm doing this now. And how's that gonna work?
And they didn't think of this."
So starting with those individual conversations
and really getting everyone on board
and showing them kind of what our vision was
and, you know, expressing our commitment
to being very collaborative and iterative with that process
and making sure that their needs are gonna get met
and we're not gonna leave anything behind,
I think, really helped us have a lot
of buy-in, support, and enthusiasm
from all of the stakeholders that we were working with.
- Yeah, and then from my experience,
I think choosing partners within the college or district
that, you know, will show up to the project,
that are engaged in their own work,
and that like to problem-solve.
And then the other piece is...
I'd say utilize the people on this panel. Like, it comes...
In terms of, you know, selling an idea
to folks on your campus,
if it comes from other leaders on campuses,
it may get buy-in
better than, say, coming from a vendor.
- I think, for us, it's working in small groups.
I think smaller groups can get a lot more work done.
And it sounds cliche,
but I think, sometimes, the hardest step is really
just that first step.
And now that we've gone live,
again, I think that kinda eased in some of the fears
that we had, or staff, right?
I think I always encourage my staff,
like, "Are we making decisions out of fear?
Or are we making decisions of the unknown?
And is the unknown fear? And why is that?"
And so I think...
Again, having daily check-ins
with the staff and also with our partners...
I think having really good communication with partners
is something that's been really reassuring for us.
I'm not a tech or a AI person at all,
and having them kinda explain things to me
in layman terms...
That's been really, really helpful for me and my staff, so.
- I'll keep mine brief.
I know you all are getting antsy for lunch.
My stomach's grumbling, too,
so I'll say, as a counselor, for me,
going back to the why
of is this going to support students and their experience
in a positive way,
if that answer is yes,
then that's what you need, right?
Like, that's the motivation,
and we all know that, right?
We're here to serve our students,
and if there's something within our institutions
that makes things more difficult for them
to be successful or to be able to get what it is
that they earned and deserve, in my case,
how can we take away some of those hurdles, right?
And everything that we've talked about
and all of our different programs are all different,
but they're all about breaking those barriers.
And so if that serves the student experience
in a positive way,
like, pff, you have all...
All of that is always gonna serve you
in completing your goals.
- Well, I wanna thank all of the panelists.
Thank you so much for sharing about what you're doing
at your institution. (audience applauds)
Thank you to our leaders and our audience here.
I hope that this has sparked some ideas for you
and you have some takeaways of maybe where you're going
to engage in some dialogue at your institutions.
And you have some resources up here if you need some help.
Sorry for volunteering you. (laughs)
But thank you again,
and lunch is downstairs in the Futures Hub,
and enjoy the rest of the conference.
Thank you.
- [Technician] Oh, check, check.
- [Audience Member] Quite a bit.
- [Technician] Anybody there?
- [Audience Member] Hi!
- [Technician] Oh, heck yeah. My room is done.